[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
okey-dokey um so welcome
to the stoa uh this is uh the second
part of our evolving ground series
in which uh we're kind of establishing
the foundation
of uh how uh our community which is also
named involving ground
uh is kind of approaching vadriana in a
contemporary way
i don't think we're going to go into a
ton of the backstory but we did do that
a bit in the first
session and so if you want to look at
that recording
it is available at evolvingground.org
so feel free to jump back there if
there's some things
or gaps that seem to come up as we're uh
moving forward
um i guess i'm your uh i've been calling
myself a steward and i realized that uh
there's actually one steward of the
stone that is peter uh so
sorry peter um i am just a facilitator
uh
but uh uh yeah that being said we're
i'll hand things off to charlie to
uh introduce herself a bit and then
we'll jump into
our topic for today thanks jared hi
everybody
um i've said this before in previous
um meetings that we've had but just a
little bit of background and
introduction
i'm a vadriana practitioner i took
ordination in a traditional lineage
and i left that context a couple of
years ago
but my name within that context that i
still use sometimes is rinsing palmo so
you might have come across that name or
come across me in that
kind of context on my blog vadriana now
[Music]
so uh a little bit about
vadriana just for anybody who's new here
um
and who's not familiar with the term as
we're presenting it here
it's um it's a life-affirming practical
spiritual training in presence of
awareness basically
um there are many hundreds of practices
each have got their own
specific function and purpose
but the general the overarching
intention
and the direction of adriana is
congruent
worldly activity um
i think worldly is a good word to use
because that covers many domains
it includes society it includes
environment other people
nature emotions there's a very broad
overarching term
and in buddhist terminology you would
maybe say something like
vajrayana trains dexterous
skillful activity in the world of form
um and that includes everyone and
everything everywhere that's kind of
buddhist way of phrasing
what we're doing
sometimes people ask about the end goal
of adriana
and personally i prefer to talk about
the effect or the result or results
because vadriana has many hundreds of
practices it has
probably thousands of practices and
those are not all the same and where
they lead
the direction that they're oriented
towards that's a continually renewed
state of presence
in activity
[Music]
and in that state of presence you could
say that
compassion and spaciousness arise
spontaneously
so there's a kind of very natural
orientation
not towards transcending the world or
leaving the world
the orientation is towards natural
congruence
and active present awareness
so spontaneity means
in this context it means sort of a
rising of its own accord you don't have
to
do anything in that state you don't have
to do something to make
compassion or competence occur it just
arises
naturally from the practice and the
training
so if you experience the result of
adriano practice
at any time compassion and spaciousness
are both there
instantaneously some of my little
introduction about how this fits into
the context of what we're
doing and what we are intending to train
in in evolving ground in
the happy yogi slack
um did i miss anything
that's kind of no i think that's good
good framing uh and yeah we we did go in
a bit
more about vadriana specifically in the
um in part one so
that's right yeah and there's
uh there also if you check out
my blog or go to the evolvingground.org
you're going to find
increasingly that we put more and more
material up there
that provides something of a context and
will help you
orient to what you know what the
community is getting up to
and what we're about
your turn
yeah um yeah i guess my brief intro is
i don't come over from a traditional uh
background it was more of a
the kind of pragmatic dharma um and
other
western variants of buddhism that that
we've seen over the
um the past i don't know
10 years or so that have started gaining
a lot of steam so
the mind illuminated uh unified
mindfulness uh and and teachers like
zhinzan young and joe rasa and daniel
ingram and all those folks
um definitely informed how i got started
um and yet uh i
um i started to notice that uh and maybe
this speaks a bit toward what we're
going to be talking about today
uh that a lot of these practices still
kind of have
you know it varying uh degrees one foot
in kind of the more renunciative
form of buddhism um and
uh and kind of transcendental uh
perspective
uh and and yeah i i guess i'm just uh
we've described ourselves as degenerates
because uh you know i know i don't have
any any uh uh urge to to remove myself
from the world and want to be in the the
messy muck
uh and and so adriana made a lot of
sense for me and
that's when i found charlie's blog and
we started chatting and
uh a year later we had decided to do
this audacious thing
of uh trying to figure out how to
take guadriana principles and and apply
them in a
contemporary setting so um yeah i guess
that's a
very brief background on me um
[Music]
and then um so yeah today so what we'll
do is we'll start by
charlie's going to give a presentation
on view and what that that means in a
buddhist context
um and then we'll uh
the two of us might discuss a little bit
uh about you know kind of whatever comes
up
and then we'll open it up to a broader
conversation and just hear your thoughts
and questions and and see what arises
thanks um so presentation in the sense
that i'm just going to ramble on for
a while and i've got a few little notes
here to remind me about
things that i thought i might say um
so uh where to start
view is uh
there's a lot to say about it really
because it's not a
um it's not a very clearly defined
concept or practice
but it is both a concept and a practice
um
and it's a very broad way of approaching
practice or understanding
[Music]
different lineages different paths
different
methods in buddhism
so view
is inseparable from
jana that is the term for path
um there are different paths one of the
way that paths are
distinguished is by describing their
view that is the world view that you
have
describes the path that you're engaging
with
and then in buddhism there's so many
paths of so many
and get into this kind of geekery of
classification
and go down the rabbit hole of defining
the 16 paths and the 34 paths and all of
the
various many difference of slightly
tweaked different
types of path in different systems so
different systems have different paths
and view
is entirely connected up with this whole
idea
of there being different paths and
it can get quite complicated and you can
get into a lot of detail about the
particular view
and what that is so um
i'm going to keep it quite broad today
but i think understanding the history of
the term is
interesting and useful um
originally it came about as a way
um this is really in the sort of
formative period
of buddhism and abhidharma it came about
as a way to describe
people who weren't on the path
so it was like kind of them and us thing
as with our view and
the heathens have their wrong view and
you know this very kind of
two-way binary classification and then
eventually
um so that that was connected to the
idea of soul
and having a soul and within buddhism
historically there has not been
the idea of a soul so the tirtika the
the them
they were the people who believed that
there was a soul
and the buddhists no self
no soul no inherent permanent sort of
um thing inside us that continues to
exist
that was the early very early kind of
formation so
then view the the way that it
uh the way that it was conceived came to
change within mahayana
and there was a lot of discussion about
different paths because
people were coming to understand that
one could be a practicing buddhist and
practice in one way or another way
and uh have
somewhat different ways of going about
it and so there was a lot of attempt at
synthesis
or attempt at trying to make things work
and figure out how
these different concepts of how life is
or what the world is like how that could
be
um reconciled so that people didn't kill
each other
basically so
in the mahayana it came to be
connected to the idea of path and
accepting different paths and different
paths within buddhism people having
different
divergences and different orientation
so like i said it's not an entirely
simple
concept or practice
so what i'm going to do is i will
try to um i'll bring some
different ideas and some different ways
of
looking at or or of coming to understand
view
um and then i'll look at
those in terms of how we view ourselves
according to different yarners or
different methods or
just by default how we view ourselves
and our emotions
and our own personal internal
experience and how we view others so
that is very much connected to
the kind of methodology that we're
training in and what we're attracted to
as as practice
and then how we relate to nature and the
environment and
the world and all of those three things
are ways that you can kind of
um unpack
what is happening with view um
so a couple of sessions ago
on the store this was so this is
actually our third
one it's number two so our first one was
number zero and
in that one i talked quite a lot about
frames of reference
and i'm not going to go over that
again in any great detail but that is
very much connected
to view so if you haven't seen
that that discussion that we had it's
called
sutra to tantra and that is
primarily that whole thing is about
frames of reference so that's
some quite useful material to bring to
this idea as
well so
frames of reference that's one way of
describing
view
another way and one which i like is to
talk about
immersion so when you have
a particular view it pervades everything
view is like the air that you breathe it
defines everything it's like how you see
everything
it's your understanding of the world
it's where where you're at
somehow so it's connected to attitude
it's connected to
demeanor to stance all of those things
they're very slightly different they
have very strong connections and
overlaps with view
so how you see other people in the world
that's very deeply connected to
your framework of reference your view
that may be hidden
so it's a nebulous it's it's a nebulous
concept it's a bit difficult to describe
um because it's so hidden
um often
often i think view isn't particularly
coherent so you can flip
between different views without
realizing it
according to what the pressures of
circumstances are
so there's this kind of modern bailey
pattern that can happen
and like where you retreat to one view
when the other one's threatened and then
you come back out to that view
once the threat's gone and that just
happens so automatically that
you don't realize that that's happening
it's like we usually have a tendency
towards one particular very dominant
view
and then some alternatives kind of
stacked up that we can use
as that one fails and we can kind of
very easily slip into and then
go back to the dominant view but we
don't notice that we don't notice that
we're doing it
we're employing views as coping
strategies in a way we've just we've
learned
our frameworks of reference in order to
be able to navigate
life and to navigate our experience
in some kind of
helpful um useful way or it seems
it has seemed that way so when view
becomes a practice
at that point you're bringing it
intentionally into conscious experience
so the idea is that when you bring this
into consciousness and you regard it as
a practice
then that's like a kind of intentional
immersion
so from the meta systematic perspective
the idea
arises it's like
the the idea arises that it's possible
to consciously move between different
systems
and to immerse yourself in one or
another or different methods
in order to fully understand what
that system is and how to come to terms
with it so there's this thing about
coming to terms with the system and for
that to occur there's this
sense of complete immersion of really
like really getting to know how all the
bits work or how
how it functions and going over and over
that and experiencing it
as it works again and again so that
you're very familiar with that it's like
you're kind of embodying
view in some sense
um in the in the buddhist context
system path method these are all words
that
pretty much relate to similar or the
same kind of things
so
your underlying view at any
point is reflected in how you see
yourself
and how you how you relate with your
emotions
and your your sensed experience
and it's connected to how you regard
other people
and your attitude your whole attitude
towards the environment
to towards society towards nature
so what i'm going to do specifically
here is look
at the difference between citric view
and tantric view which we've already
done
some before but this is going to be a
theme that
that comes through this whole series
and is recurring again and again um
but i'm i'm doing this specifically to
sort of just go into detail about how
views can be different
but it's also a way of
um it's giving away
to when you're looking at books reading
books or when you're hearing other
people speak or giving presentations or
whatever that you can begin
to start distinguishing you know
particularly in a
buddhist or a spiritual context start
distinguishing between
what are what are the views that are
informing
or what is the dominant view that is
informing this particular person's
presentation you this is um
this is something you could go into a
lot more detail like not just sutra not
just tantra these are just very very
broad categories
[Music]
if you are familiar with david's work
david chapman's work at meaningless.com
you can also look at view in terms of
monism eternalism legalism dualism
and these are all very common views that
we tend to slip
in between and which we use
invisibly we they kind of go unnoticed
so part of the work that he's doing
there is bringing
those views into consciousness
so that they can be much better
understood as informing the way that
people
work the way that people address
problems the way that we
relate and the way that we write books
or whatever
so i just wanted to make the point that
the views that i am going to
look at in more detail here are just two
of
many many many even within buddhism
and i like i like to look at these two
because
they're very broad and so they they
describe this kind of
really quite broad way of relating and
they're not difficult to pick up
once you're really aware of these um
different kind of orthogonal ways of
relating to things then you can begin to
spot them a lot lot easier i think
and i would like to go into zog chen
view a little as well but we may or may
not have
time for that and maybe jared will um
have something that he can say
about that later as well
so um thinking about view
in relation to self so personal stuff
our internal world our way of
um all of our sense fields and our
cognition and everything that is
personal and
in in the cetric view
the kind of encapsulation of the view is
that uncontrolled emotions
are preventing you from freedom
from liberation from enlightenment
emotions particularly turbulent emotions
desire
anger they
they become obstacles you view those as
obstacles
to your liberation so cetric view is
reflected in the way that you think
about your emotional life
your time yourself it's a project
it's a project that you're working on so
the
analogy that i thought of in this
context was
it's like a sculpture you're you're
um working to make this beautiful
perfect sculpture and you're chipping
away at the bits
that you don't want you're kind of
intricately involved in perfecting this
beautiful
pure work of art and you know
the bits that you chop off or whatever
in the bits that you're you're
honing away those are just completely
irrelevant you're what you're
focused on and the way that you're
working is just creating this
beautiful eventually perfect
pure um
object if you like or in the sense
of practice it's subject um
so there's this idea of perfection of
ultimate purity
you're training your self towards and
that is no self that is
um you know there's this flip that
occurs because eventually
you hone everything away
so there's this sort of sense of the
ideal of perfection
but eventually what that becomes is
cessation or
complete cessation of sensation it's
emptiness
so the perfect sculpture is when there's
no material
left it's just emptiness maybe a bit of
a crass analogy but
i wanted to get this project idea
established in relation to sutra
so not that tantra doesn't have projects
there are many
many sort of activities and projects the
view which informs those is somewhat
different
so cetric view establishes this goal
of purity of self of nonduality of self
of experience of no self um
or emptiness of self that is
fundamentally different
from ordinary experience now
with tantra rather than uncontrolled
emotions preventing
liberation so the the emotions must be
pacified or tamed or calmed
tantra regards emotions as kind of
messed up
like they've been convoluted and
constrained and scrunched and
squidged so they've somehow been sort of
shoved into this sort of tight
restricted highly limited
form is sometimes referred to as
neuroses or distorted or unenlightened
quality and personally i don't really
like those terms it's like the emotional
experience
the the view is that the emotional
experience has been
violently constricted by an enforced
habitual
compulsive mode or response
and that's so instantaneous it's hard to
see ourselves doing that
but that is the thing within tantric
view that is seen to be the cause of the
limitation
so the tantric view towards self and
emotions
is that we've done this this is
something that we've done
and the review that the view sorry
is reflected in wanting to engage
with those emotions in order to change
who and how we are so there's still this
idea of liberation
and particularly in outer tantra there's
a lot about purifying and
perfecting and you know there's still
this that idea is still there
but it's much more mundane and messy
tantra is
way more messy than sutra
and the view is that liberation or
transformation
transformation is the principle which
the view informs
so transformation is through involvement
with the ordinary everyday emotional
experience because there is this view of
what we have done and how emotions are
that
changes the way that we're going to work
with them
so in order for transformation to occur
there has to be
involvement it just doesn't happen at a
distance
there isn't there's not an observer that
you're creating that is
relating to an object you're getting in
there
involved you're
allowing the space for transformation to
occur
because um with with sutra view
most meditation methods are informed by
sutra they emphasize calming
and pacifying emotions tantra is often
mistaken
um from that perspective tantra
mistaken to be about expression
because the opposite of renouncing and
calming is thought to be
owning and expressing so it's seen to be
different
and the difference that's perceived from
that perspective is
oh it's about getting into your emotions
and expressing and
and you know having them and whatever
so we're not talking about opposites
here so tantra isn't opposite to sutra
it's kind of orthogonal to sutra it's
meta
like historically it was meta to suture
it's a way of stepping outside
a sutra view there's a different
paradigm there's
not a continuation of sutra
it's different in principle that's a
really important point to understand
about the difference in tantric
view it's different in principle it's
not a continuation it's not an expansion
so with regards to emotions that means
that you're
engaging and becoming familiar with the
somatic experience of emotion
in order to have more choice available
to you
than basic compulsive expression or
repression or distraction
or ignoring so you're not calming
you're engaging in order
for that relationship to change
so the way that we restrict and
constrain our emotional experiences very
individual
the tantric view towards emotions that
there are contortions that there are
distortions of their natural state
means that the practice occurs
in the presence of the emotion
so that is a big difference so with
sutra the
your your work or your practice is
without
the presence of the emotion you're
finding the space
without the arising emotion and that's
where your practice is with tantra
your practice is with the presence of
the arising emotion
so you're finding space with that you're
not rejecting it or ignoring it
not calming
so when you get really skillful at that
you can channel the emotion effectively
so for example with anger you feel the
anger
you understand the nature of the
arriving motion you kind of understand
it experientially i mean
and you find the liberated quality of
the emotion which is
clarity maybe or you know some kind of
um
it's very clearing experience and there
is a choice
there and then maybe there's an
expression maybe there's
a direct passionate statement which
is it's just also going to be obviously
kind because you have the spaciousness
there so expression of emotion in
buddhist hunter is never
righteous it's not mean you know
expression of emotion is not going to be
mean or vindictive or terrified or
peevish
because it's just always based in
spaciousness and spaciousness is
kindness
so with tantra and this is different to
zogchen as well
so there's often a time gap there's a
time gap between the arising
of the emotion and the internal response
because
you're there is some work there there is
practice
you're allowing the spaciousness to be
there
um maybe that's expression eventually
maybe it isn't
there's always this choice
so that was um
there's a question that i think might be
worth worth addressing
now uh siddharth did you did you want to
mute yourself and ask your question
or i can ask it for you
your mic is coming from so uh when you
say that tantra is not
uh not a continuation of sutra
is that what hold on i lost it
is that with reference to the view
associated with each path
or with the paths themselves i know
sometimes it's said that the result of
sutra is the base of tatra
right so it's both continuation not a
continuation and i
am emphasizing the difference
at this moment but so it is continuation
in that sense but it is
uh what i wanted to emphasize with the
difference
in the sense that it is a different
paradigm it's a different way of working
so when we're talking about view view
is what makes the difference
so view is the sort of hub
of the discontinuation the discontinuity
so often and again the reason i'm
emphasizing the difference is because
often the difference is kind of
um covered over in some sense in order
for things to seem
harmonious and continuous and and often
tantra is viewed
from the perspective of sutra so what
i'm doing here is viewing sutra from the
perspective of tantra
and viewing tantra from its own
perspective in its own right
so from this view there is a
discontinuity
but it's a really good question because
that's you know that is the usual
presentation is yeah the
end point of sutra is the beginning
point of tantra and that's also
important so thanks for
thanks for raising that yeah
so i kind of waffled on a bit about the
different views in relation to self
and to you know personal
emotion and personal experience and what
have you so
taking this into the realm of others the
way that you view others
sutra views others as trapped and
suffering in the same way that
we are with our emotions and experience
so the way that sutra views our self is
also reflected in the way that
sutra views other people and other
people and
you know people that we're relating with
whether we know them or not
so people are trapped people are
suffering suffering is
horrible it sucks and we can get out of
it that is the
the sutra view
because in this view you have some
understanding
of how things work as a practitioner
then there's a clearly defined way you
know
this defined way that you're going to
end suffering and liberate yourself
might take a very very long time but
you're on that project so in some
sense you regard yourself as
different to others in the same way that
your
liberated self is different to and
separate from
your emotional obstacles your own
impurities
so in that way the purity of your own
self is is separate from and different
to others as well so
your pure self is pitying of others
who um are in this same horrible
slush pile of nasty suffering and
you have compassion for others because
your view
is that they are suffering you view them
as trapped like parts of yourself
that you're seeing as obstacles and as
trapped
and so this is how meta practice comes
about it's about curing for
purifying purifying your own impurities
and your own negative
karma through magically purifying others
of theirs
as well you're bringing good will and
purity and light and benevolent
intention into your interactions with
others
in order to assist in the project of
getting rid of suffering
and bad feelings it's a meta matter is
very much tied up with sutrick view
of others there's this purification
um principle and this this idea of
bringing wholesomeness
and the view of others is informed by
the idea that suffering is the natural
condition
and that it's possible to escape from it
you're renouncing suffering
so that your your view is that you're
moving beyond suffering
there's a way out others can escape from
it as well and your purpose
is to bring relief to others by
distancing even from the idea of
suffering
that's very much emphasized in centric
view
and that can be a very very helpful
wholesome practice if you've
you know if you're going through a
time or whatever
in tantra because tantric view towards
how the world is and ourself and our
emotions is very different it's also
different in relation to others so in
tantra you're not rejecting your own
impurities and inadequacies
as such you're continuing to experience
and feel the messiness
of your emotional world there's no
clearly defined thing between this is a
good emotion this is a bad emotion it's
just all
a jumble of different
you know a lot of incoherence there and
your view
of others experiences that their view is
equally messy and unpredictable as
your own so with tantric practice
you're engaging with all the qualities
of your own being
so the view towards others is that
you're engaging with all their
qualities too you're not assisting or
purifying
other people with your own purity you're
dancing with them
you're recognizing and engaging with
their individual quirks and
personalities because
how you relate to yourself is
non-renunciative
so also that view manifests
in relationship with others
so with yourself you're opening up space
for
choicefulness with regards to your
emotions and your experience and that's
the same towards others you're looking
for the space
making it available for them you're
engaging with who
and how they happen to be in the moment
and accepting their emotions and their
constraints
as just being a part of the play
of how we
human how we are you know how we relate
in the world so the tantric view towards
others is that rather
than rejecting anyone you're seeking to
understand because
transformation can't occur without first
understanding so again there's
this sense of a kind of time lag in the
work that you're doing in your practice
it takes time
from the initial recognition and
engagement to get to the point
where transformation can occur because
you're you're having to
find the space like we were
getting back to the question that
somebody asked there you find a space
that's
that's the starting point that's the
base for tantric practice
you find the space in the interaction
so is that i'm going to go on to talking
about relationship with the world and
environment and nature and stuff but
any questions that particularly arise in
relation to
relations
no nothing coming up looks like alf has
his
hand or up nope uh some
isil go ahead if you have
there you go yeah uh thanks secretary
thanks charlie
uh quick question this might address it
um
later but i was wondering is there any
recommendation in terms of the
personality
or um the way people behave and what
kind of
uh sutra tantric
practices is better for them based on
their personality or
stage of stage of evolution
yeah that's interesting um you know i
think
well from the tantric perspective
personality is really important
and um your personality in some sense
is your practice it's very much
connected to your
your practice in sutra that is not so
much
the case in sutra there's a general a
general answer that is
applicative to everybody so you're
aiming towards a
[Music]
sameness rather than difference so
i think it would be
i think it would be appropriate for
somebody to practice according to
which of those views they feel is most
resonant
i think the the sutric view can be
that can be very helpful if you are
you know if you are in a position where
life actually has been pretty and
you you know you're having a lot of
difficulty in dealing or
you know just things are just being
constantly thrown at you so much that
you know it can actually be really
helpful to take respite
and it can be very very helpful to
work within a very clear set
system and structure and so if you're
if you are not used to systems if you're
not used
to
conforming yourself to a system you
don't know how to do that then sutra can
be fabulous
that can be really great if your life
has been
if your life's pretty chaotic or if
you're kind of pulled in one direction
or another or
you know and and you've never had that
experience of
learning how to systematize then i think
sutra practice is just
fabulous for that it really really can
help
people just become more
systematized as beings
and you know some of the some of the
sutra
organizations and approaches are very
very good at doing that
you know like going because goenka's
approach
is very good at that tmi i think is
probably really great at helping people
systematize um
uh we have another one from mauro uh
maybe i'll just say it just so we can
move forward um
what are the practical differences
between a tantrica and a sutra
practitioner
uh with relation to others if you could
give
some specific example uh that'd be great
that'd be great yeah
well in the extreme a sushi practitioner
is in a monastery
sitting in their little meditation box
so they can stay awake all night
or stay aware all night whatever or you
know
that the sort of archetypal extremes of
you know the the tantrica
is the chad who's
like you know bring it on bring it on
you know i'm a hero i can do all of this
you know
uh i have infinite compassion i have
infinite generosity
and you know the archetypal
suit this is the view from tantra
obviously the archetypal sutra
practitioner is somebody who is
you know really very careful
very considered very
cautious in relation to
the potential danger and
implosion and explosion of stuff
so there's a lot of taming there
um and yeah you might go to a monastery
to
really spend quite a lot of time in
contemplative
practice you know really slowing things
down a lot
paying a lot of attention to every
moment
so the the sutra and when that gets
translated into sort of ordinary
everyday life the citric view
is to really like pay
deliberate attention to what is going on
like constantly renew this
um what's happening now
this you know there's a slight sort of
um objectification there
in terms of observing and bringing
observation or
noticing or whatever so
uh yeah yeah i'm sort of
caricaturing the tantrica and the
practitioner so a couple other quick
ones
uh purple uh you say if uh
if sutra has general answers that apply
to everyone does that mean that
tantra has specific answers that are
different for everyone yes
i think yeah that would that we could
just give a yep
uh and then another one from robert uh
stonehill what is the ultimate
motivation for action and tantra
assuming that purification is the
ultimate motivation for sutra
the the motivation is
in buddhist terms it is i'm trying not
to use buddhist terms here but in
buddhist terms the the motivate
motivation comes from the idea of the
unification of compassion and wisdom
so the motivation is already
based in
spaciousness and spaciousness naturally
gives rise to
compassion and so the motivation for
tantra
is often regarded as compassion
and
i think i'd like to look at it in terms
of active
engagement so the motivation is much
more about
being creative it's about creative um
the motivation is to create good stuff
basically
create good useful um
appropriate congruent
um interrelations
um you know appropriate congruent
relationships and
organizations and institutions and
social
opportunities and blah you know it's
about
the the direction of tantra is
congruence
about congregant activity so the
motivation
coming from spacious awareness is always
about
wanting to have that kind of engagement
and i would just also say too it's it's
um
we're we're speaking of the caricatures
of sutra and tantra
uh and you know pretty much uh
any any lineages or or teachings or
systems that you're gonna run into today
um they are very blended uh you know
uh in a very extreme sense uh
you know if you're a hardcore sutrick
practitioner that might mean that
uh you know emotions of all sort are
just forbidden uh you know charlie i
think you told me about
running into some uh theravadan uh monks
in tibet and you know they they just
they're fit the stone cold face like
they
they are completely removed from any of
the the human element
um but mahayana which is is kind of
more a more common uh you know
it includes some of this emotion but
it's you know
specifically uh you know the heartful
emotion
uh the meta uh you know and so it's kind
of
starting to include uh emotion but not
but with limits
um and so yeah this this is seeing
things on the spectrum i think is really
helpful
um and yeah it just it does really get
messy in a lot of ways that's a really
good way of looking at it and then the
so then the the next little step on from
that mahayana
is the outer tantra and that and that
starts to just um have more
of the relationship with oh emotions
that previously were kind of
seen as a bit negative or whatever but
there's still the purifying aspect there
so
that's and that's a really great way of
putting it jared thank you
yeah good view so
thinking about how view
affects our relationship with nature and
the environment and the world
at large so traditionally
very traditionally like jared was just
saying in the sutrix view
your um the view towards the world is
that you
are aiming to leave it and if at all
possible you do that while you're still
here
i'm not kidding i'm not you know this is
the citric view is to leave this
world so sutra has this kind of
minimalist
quality to it you're uncluttering your
environment
to make it a conducive habitat for you
to nurture
your your virtuous side your pure sides
you
like for example you don't want babies
around they're going to mess things up
and make it extremely difficult
because they'll be getting in the way
and uh
anything that gets in the way of
attaining pure
pure life and enlightenment with this
kind of capital e
is non-conducive to the path so
sometimes you get these kind of
compromises where it's like
well yeah okay you know you can still
practice and have babies and stuff but
it will be harder and
will take a lot longer and that kind of
thing
so it is actually very hard to practice
sutra sincerely with babies and and
stuff around and there's a very good
reason for that
it's you know citric view traditionally
was anti-natalist
you took vows of celibacy you went off
to a monastery
your environment was honed to reflect
the the purity of emptiness so for
people
practicing that path sex and
families and being in the world
was just like a big no-no um
so a very interesting thing happens with
the view towards
nature in sutra there's this kind of
distinct split that occurs
so
this is a maybe a bit more of a
traditional view but
you would regard all of nature as
disgusting this this is really explicit
in the sutras
it's gross it's worldly it's
non-conducive to practice
animals are dumb and less lucky than you
are in your
fortunate precious human rebirth there's
this kind of sense that
the body is gross there are practices
that
cultivate the view of the body is really
disgusting and horrible and you have
this
same view towards nature it's full of
horrible creepy
creepy crawlies and that
they reflect how you yourself are
captured into
habitual compulsive cycles of of pattern
and response that you want to get away
from you want to escape
but on the other hand i think and
looking at sutra in its modern
contemporary context
i think a very different kind of split
has happened it's really interesting
as it has become modernized you get this
kind of
opposite view of nature it's coming from
romanticism it's sort of incorporating
idealism and romanticism
into buddhist approaches and you get
this kind of saccharine
pure very kitsch attitude that is
separating you from the reality
and the messiness of nature you get this
kind of
um it's it's stripping nature of
anything dangerous and dirty
sees only the beauty only and there's a
kind of distance there
so you're romanticizing and observing
from a distance
and then you can kind of reset that you
can regard nature as very pure
as well so there's this split into the
world is
either kind of gross and horrible or
there's this sort of thing that's been
brought from the western tradition into
regarding the world as sort of very pure
and beautiful and
um not having that kind of nastiness
and that reflects the citric view
towards the self it's like you strip the
self of all the
dangerous stuff of anything
uncontrollable and unpredictable
um i think
with sutrick view when you when you
really take centric view on
um sincerely there's also this kind of
danger
that you might start role playing into
this sort of pure self
and sometimes i think when sutrick
viewers
is scorned or
when it's looked at as as being sort of
oh no
or whatever that what's happening is
that
people we're seeing we're seeing
a sort of false presentation
of sutrick view there's like this sort
of virtuous holy good
self that's prescribed and very
confirming and confining
um a matter i think that's one of the
ways that the sutra
view can backfire it can become in
it can sort of prescribe this very fixed
personality that people
try to model themselves into or
you know that we might try to um
mold ourselves into being this kind of
fixed personality
and so tantra backfires in a very
different kind of way
what what tends to happen with tantric
view
is that the expression of
emotion is mistaken as the practice
because you're doing all this work to
embrace and engage with your emotions
and especially if that's invaluable and
revelatory and it can be revelatory if
you're coming from
having practiced a lot of sutra that can
be a really
valuable and and um useful experience
and then
what can happen is you get into this
cycle of immediate compulsive expression
which is kind of very ironic of course
because that's exactly what
sutra trains you to avoid so it can
seem like when you're stepping into
tantra and you're
transitioning your view into tantric
view that you're
you have this sort of liberated
expression of emotion and your sudden
you know you're in touch with all your
emotions and it's fabulous and
you're just kind of vomiting them all
over everybody um
it's not uncommon when when somebody's
actually
beginning to make that move
from sutra practice into tantric
practice and the inter-tantric view
that can happen very naturally at a
certain point
like if you've been living an ordinary
life engaging with the world
but not you know trying to sort of
restrict your emotions or
behave in a very sort of dissociated
detached
way and then you open up to tantric view
you can get this kind of backlash that
is not uncommon
you've not been used to embracing your
emotion and sensation so you've been
trying to pacify it and calm it and then
you get to figure out
something about the nature of
renunciative frameworks and view
being maybe not what you want and then
in that situation kind of
total compulsive expression can it can
feel very liberating it can feel like
that is the practice
i've kind of gone off track to where
were they so yeah the tantric view
towards
nature and the environment so
the tantric relationship with
environment with the natural world is
interesting
it's all about creativity um
metaphorically or
maybe even literally you know maybe
you're a gardener you're nurturing
you're
assessing you're tweaking you're giving
space for things to grow
you're cultivating something in the
inner direction so you're changing
circumstances with
with tantric relationship with the world
you're changing circumstances to give
the world
around you the best chance to grow it's
like you're watering it
making sure that there's some light
there there's a lot of involvement
but you're not focused on the outcome
you're engaged in the process
so you may have an overall kind of
intention or purpose you may have
a sense of where you're heading but you
don't always know
how you're going to get there there's
this kind of looseness
again it's about playfulness it's about
a willingness toward
trial and error towards tweaking things
so
you'll often hear people referring to
tantric practice as being like dancing
and the result is being fluidity
this is pertinent in relationship with
the the environment because
it's engaged creative play the view
towards the environment as having this
sort of
unpredictable messy chaotic
gorgeous everything
quality is it that
view if you review if if you view the
environment
in that way then that gives rise to
a relationship that involves engaged
creative play
that that all comes out of your
meditation practice that's the direction
that your meditation
leads so she named practice that we're
referring to here or opening practice is
always the base
for something else in tantric practice
it's never
the the end thing
it's always the foundation it's always
the ground for
the next way of relating or
the next practice or it's always there
as the ground
of your practice and the ground of
experience in meditation provides the
security and the self-reliance so a lot
of tantric practice is about developing
self-reliance really it's the confidence
it's about developing confidence for you
to
engage and transform the world around
you into a vivid
live colorful productive active
productivity so you can't be distant
to engage in that way you're going to
get your hands mucky you're not fixed in
relation to the world around you
you're not the same from one moment to
the next you're
not cultivating equanimity and sameness
of response to things so equanimity
equanimity and transformation don't
match very well
transformation occurs with spacious
passionate involvement
you bring spaciousness to tantric
practice much more than you would bring
equanimity your medic meditation is
cultivating
spaciousness and spaciousness cultivates
creative
activity and i think it's worth
recognizing that relative to
relative to the dissociative and
disengaged renunciative
view this relational view is actually
pretty threatening
by comparison when it's viewed from the
the the view that is cultivating
equanimity
you you can't do this
you can do when you're cultivating
equanimity you can't
uh you can't you can't relate to the
world in the same way so again this is
emphasizing the difference
in views here you can't romanticize
the world if you're really fully engaged
you can't um you know you have to have
some sort of distance there to be able
to do that
tantric view is very realist in that
sense a very
pragmatic it's involved engagement with
things as they are it's not kind of
climbing
some neatly prepared steps with railings
to a scenic view with a signpost telling
you
where the scenic view is and then a big
board at the top saying scenic view
so that you know that's kind of very
reassuring you know that you've got the
scenic view
you know that that's what that is tantra
isn't
tantra just doesn't do that it's a very
different
view in that way it's not very scenic
i would say charlie that the equanimity
component
the only way i see it fitting in here in
the transition is that
um spaciousness itself
is equinamious in the sense that it
doesn't have it doesn't have much of an
agenda
yeah right but that and and that kind of
creates
you know if we're using this dancing
metaphor um
you know you need space to dance in
uh and and the more spaciousness is in
the
you know the bigger the dance floor uh
the more possibility there is uh
for movement and interaction um
yeah so yeah it but that does not mean
that that we're dispassionately uh and
and completely
equanimous with uh the the actual
dancing
uh we're actually fully engaged with it
yeah
i think um equanimity has become very
much associated with
calmness don't you think
yeah for sure yeah i think yeah so
like you're saying maybe the tantric
view towards equanimity is more to do
with
um equality of
stuff arising something like that it
kind of
shifts the emphasis somehow i think
yeah i don't know maybe i should just
kind of stop
waffling now and we can should we have
our
yeah i know we're well let's see here
we're uh
oh we are at an hour okay cool uh for a
second i thought we were already at our
time but now that
that works perfect um let's see here uh
questions maybe we can open up some
questions here
um and todd uh if you've seen anything
specific uh that you think would be good
to start with because
yeah todd is helping us
[Music]
navigate the chat because sometimes a
lot of chat happens and
it's not always possible to sort of keep
track of what's happening there so
so todd is our um
man in the chat with kids
yeah hey
look were you there todd i heard you for
a second
yeah no i'm sorry i thought you were
about to say something so i was i was
holding
off here go for it um sure yeah so that
uh there's a there's a couple here i
think uh first there's a
question from uh from purple that i
think is is good to
get into a little bit is uh is chine
ever an end
to itself or is it always the base of
something else
what she knew as a practice has its own
result
um but i mean there's no point
practicing it unless
um it's the base for something else
you know it's not uh
you know within itself it has the result
that is a particular kind of spacious
presence
um but yeah that's not
that's not an end that's a starting
point really
and the spacious presence in the context
of one that does not exclude the dance
uh things are still happening in the
spaciousness
uh whereas you know something like
cessation uh that that is in the citric
it's a the result of a lot of the sutra
method um
you know it is there's nothing there
it's just just
spaciousness um and with without
anything arising within it
um right so yeah so it's spaciousness in
the sense that thoughts don't arise but
you're you still have sensation
um when you're practicing shine you know
you're still hearing sounds and you know
some
uh states in the citric path will
lead you to a place which which is
the end point as well is it's connected
to the end point so it's very different
in that sense that
you you're not hearing you're not
experiencing sensation you're not
um you know all of your sensations are
pacified so yeah sheena doesn't
you don't um you know sensation might
change a lot with shine practice because
you are simply
simply allowing it to occur naturally
without
sort of that conceptual grip that often
shrouds it but um
yeah so concept just naturally seems to
die down
like thoughts naturally
dissolve because that's what they do
when they have space around them
i noticed uh nicole you said tantric
practice sounds more
unification oriented than suture
practice
yeah i think that that's a perfect way
of describing it um yeah that i think
uh you know yogi uh which which is kind
of alluding to this yoking
uh whereas yeah the the tantra is is
yoking
uh the result of of sutra
with everything else uh so that they
become kind of
inseparable in some sense and in
in traditional terminology you would say
tantric practice is the unification of
emptiness and form or
the the non-duality of wisdom and
compassion
and unification is often you know in the
inner tantras that's connected to
um unification of male and female and
there are a lot of sexual
imagery there as well so yeah
unification is sort of a very
traditional
description of tantrum goal
yeah even with like the the statues uh
you know so
in the sutra route it's the the solo
buddha
in this is with his pleasant smile uh of
just kind of
being okay with everything in in his in
in isolation
uh and one of the uh the the tantric uh
uh the common tantric
statues is is the yabyan which is uh
you know a male and female uh having sex
in unification so yeah it's very very
explicit
uh but the male and female to charlie's
point the male and female
um is is a uh
is symbolic in the sense of talking
about this very fundamental
uh experience of emptiness or you could
call it nebulosity or openness
uh and then form or pattern or order
or material um so yeah
they they are definitely to be taken
symbolic even though a lot of
tantric practices use them in literal uh
in a more of a literal fashion
let's see here jared i think there was a
a question from uh sarah a little bit
ago here around china
and i don't know sarah did you want to
ask that the question around flattening
a preference landscape
sure um so that one was kind of when
people were asking about
equanimity i remember on one call you
said
something about like flattening a
preference landscape
or something when you're doing shine and
and maybe that was about just
where your awareness or attention goes
or kind of like what arises
but but it sounds like that would be
different from
somehow changing yourself so that you
feel the same way about whatever comes
up
right yeah so i remember that
conversation that was about
um the so that was addressing the idea
in concentrative meditation that there's
a sort of
central focus or and very often that is
quite internal so there's this idea of
center and periphery
so it's unbalanced in that sense
so with shino practice there's the
the idea that you are not giving
particular um
priority to any aspect
of experience
so you don't prioritize your nose
you don't prioritize your breath you
don't prioritize
yourself in this body but you don't not
um maintain awareness of all of those
things so there's a kind of um
it's not flattening so much as like we
were saying equalness maybe or
you know as far as your sense fields
extend
then that is where your awareness is so
the tendency as well when one starts
practicing machining goes from
practicing sort of very concentrative
method into practicing
a more opening style of meditation is
that your mind starts kind of popping
around
so it's that thing and then that thing
and that and there's a sort of sense of
um you're awareness being kind of very
flitty
and that gradually dies down because
you're that
you know things want to grab
things kind of arise and that is in a
sense sort of grabbing of awareness
and then the practice releases that so
that
there's no particular priority
prioritization things can just arise
and they arise in the space so the felt
sense
is
yeah i guess equanimous in that sense
yeah the i think the the equanimous uh
um to what charlie was saying before i
think there's a connotation that gets
put on top of it which is to be which is
calmness right or like a certain
demeanor
um and so it's like it can be this weird
thing
we're kind of play acting equanimity
which is like oh if i don't care about
anything then i
react to it all the same um and there's
kind of a bit of an agenda being
brought up but yeah the strange thing is
is if you if there really is
um if there isn't a preferential
treatment or a prescribed way of
interacting
with what comes up in experience then
the quality of what arises is kind of
not defined by you i suppose in the
sense that
sometimes if i'm sitting in a sheena and
there's
you know motorcycles flying by the the
uh the thing and maybe my wife's on a
conference call and
she's frustrated and i can hear you know
all of a sudden
things are very energetic and kind of um
lively and and almost a little chaotic
but that is because
that is the environment is kind of
chaotic so if i were to prescribe
my reaction to it by saying i'm going to
be
you know i have to relate to this in a
certain way
that's when we might go wrong and yet i
think
real equanimity um can be found
in spaciousness in open space because it
doesn't have any agenda but but yeah i
think that our mistake is when we
we get an idea of what that what
equanimity is and we start to play
active
if that makes any sense
yeah and there's no there's no
prioritization of focus
either so like that situation that you
described just then
it would be very easy if you're if
you're trying to maintain focus
on your breath and maintain this kind of
you know very calm
consistent relationship with the breath
and then all this stuff's going on you
know that's going to be distracting it's
going to be irritating
whereas if the
if the emphasis on focus is taken away
and there's just no
idea that there has to be a particular
focus
then everything just arises
without that kind of priority
so i think there's some interesting back
and forth in the the chat around
uh tantra and psychotherapy nicole did
you want to ask that question that you
had from a few minutes back
sure yeah um yeah so i was as i was
listening i was just kind of jumping
to um what i know about uh sort of like
freud and psychotherapeutic
practice uh based on all of the research
that has been done in the past
century or so by these like
psychologists
uh specifically in regards to repression
and specifically in regards to like uh
what not allowing our desires to
be unleashed how that causes us to be
unhealthy in certain respects and can
cause
um psychopathy i was wondering if
you think perhaps that uh that's sort of
leaning more so
in the direction of uh tantric uh
view uh rather than sort of like oh
i guess my question was and i remembered
um
would you say that tantric practice
based on this recent research
is more in line with human nature um
rather than cyclic practice
yes
um i would say too that it's always
important to
realize that uh i think um
like we were talking about spectrum wise
uh a lot of the different since there's
so many different types of therapy
uh and and psychotherapy uh some of them
you might find sutrick elements in some
and you might find tantric elements and
others
um and and yeah i think to your point
a lot of the the shadow work type things
uncovering what we have repressed or
were ashamed of
um does kind of go in a tantric route of
you know
wanting to work with it wanting to
include it in our experience
um and yet at the same time sometimes
you could even if if the goal
of of uncovering it is to get rid of it
um then that might be you know
some sort of amalgamation of the two you
know or we want to purify it we want to
get rid of it as opposed to transforming
it into something else
um so yeah it's hard to to clearly put
it in
in either camp but there's yeah you can
you can use that the tantric citric
lens to look at things and get a bit of
a flavor of where they oriented
so i like uh christian's uh question
here in chat
around uh goodness and congruence and
and who defines that christian do you
want to go ahead and ask that
yeah i can ask that real quick i just
need to
scroll up to it
um well the question was i can't find it
it was about
well you mentioned that goodness and
congruence are kind of the motivating
objectives of the creative play in the
tantric view
and where when that earlier question
about motivation for action was asked
and i was wondering how goodness or
congruence is defined if it's defined
within the view or if that's something
that's left up to the
tantric practitioner or or how those two
ideas may be
okay right i see so yeah this idea of
congruence
is um is coming
from
the um it's from the end point of the
meditation
series which is spontaneous congruent
action and that is really the
um that is the result
of tantric practice in some ways in the
base
of zogchen practice so
um
it's congruence so
this is a question that i think a lot
about and that i've
i've kind of gone backwards and forwards
a lot over
um over the years i don't think that
there
is an automatic
like if you experience the result of
tantric practice if you experience
uh rigpa um if you experience like
presence of awareness
that doesn't necessarily mean that you
are going to behave perfectly or
always act in the best way or whatever
so the practice
after being
after having the experience of presence
awareness from meditation which is
always
a practice which requires renewing in
some sense never fixed
never fixed so the practice after that
is learning and training how to relate
that in the world as you go about
ordinary activity how to maintain that
state and how to translate that
into congruent
response and that isn't automatic it's
not prescribed
it's not prescribed as this is the way
that you do it
and the very nature of the world makes
that impossible
so there's always a random
element there's always something
unpredictable
you're never going to have perfect
information and so it's always going to
be possible to
you know your motivation might be there
and your awareness might be there
but things can just kind of still
pan out wrong so that's very much
built into the the whole of the
vajrayana perspective of how things
are you cannot ever
have perfection
it just simply is not something that
is going to be
consistently constantly available
as activity you know there's always
going to be this kind of
play and fluidity and you know there can
always be
different kinds of skill or a better
sort of skill so
as i suppose a little bit like um
continuing positive feedback loops you
know
that could be an infinite loop it's not
something that
is going to end at some point
in yeah
perfect experience yeah
to keep coming back to the dancing
metaphor um
you know i think
we all know what it looks like uh when
somebody
is when the the the dance is too
prescribed
uh it's too constrained it's not
creative it can't ever change or evolve
uh to the circumstances um
and so when we include spontaneity in
there or creativity
uh through uh finding that that
spaciousness
uh and possibility um and kind of get
out of our own ways
then we kind of get into something maybe
like looks like a little bit like a flow
state
um and so you know to be in to have
presence of awareness to be at the the
end of
this meditation series uh might mean
that it's very easy for you to flow
and to dance very fluidly and and and
without kind of hesitation and a lot of
confidence and things like that
and yet every time you're dancing uh
you're practicing and figuring out how
to continually develop
the skills of dancing um
and and then there's no yeah there's no
end to that
uh to how good we get at working with
our
methods and and openness to creative
uh spontaneous action right yeah so like
an
analogy that you're reminding me of is
like skiing
and you know you watch somebody skiing
over new terrain or down
you know uh down different sorts of
mountain sides of whatever there's
always something different there they're
always kind of responding
in a way and it's kind of just beautiful
to watch
because there's this kind of congruence
between the activity in the environment
and there's a sort of dancing
relationship with the environment and i
really like that kind of analogy for
it's you know you couldn't say that that
is
fixed perfect end point in any way it's
just
somebody being very skillfully
you know with this kind of fabulous
capacity that they've developed
to be able to relate to their particular
environment
nicole i um i was thinking about your
question
wanting to come back to that um
there is so i think the the answer that
jared gave was really good
it's um
[Music]
there's this whole western tradition and
there's a lot of question around how
how does it relate and how do we relate
the whole history of psychology and the
whole history of western
western civilization in some way with
what we're inheriting from buddhist
traditions and a lot of people do a lot
of
very good work in that area
some people look at synthesis and people
emphasize the differences
so you know i just wanted to say yeah
this is a whole really big field
some of the people doing really good
work in this area michael taft
is you know he's bringing a
really deep
personal experience from the buddhist
background and he's working with people
who are
looking at psychology and how that
relates
who else is doing that i'm blocking on
his name
who's michael works with at the moment
who's been on his podcast
uh the one who does glimpses
lock lock lock black kelly yeah
right so he's also he's also looking at
the synthesis
and he's got deep experience in both
areas you know in both traditions so
he's somebody you might be interested to
look into as well
[Music]
i i also like to emphasize the
differences a lot you know i'm always
going on about differences
so i think it's really worthwhile
looking at a system in itself and
understanding like having the immersive
experience
understanding how that system works um
you know maybe narrowing sometimes
rather than
trying to figure out everything in
comparison to each other and
and merge everything so i think it's
sort of well worth
it you know doing a little bit of
shopping around whatever and then
finding a system
that really seems to resonate and then
going more
into that one and exploring it as well
um and there's also the other thing that
came to mind is
some david's pages on buddhism for
vampires the shadow
shadow work which isn't the same it's
not the same as
tantric practice but there are very
interesting
similarities like and i think it's
eating the shadow and
all of that series
as there's been some interesting back
and forth in the chat here for the last
few minutes
about uh a question from michael tapps
recent stoa sarah did you want to go
ahead and start that question off and
see if
we can get charlie and jared's thoughts
on it
yeah so this was on october 6th i
listened to
michael taft on the stoa and
um i don't remember whether he was
someone i think asked a question about
either shinzo young or the manasseh
academy maple and they're
they're tied in together um and
michael taft said they're describing
stuff dualistically
and then pushing people into the nondual
view
and i'm wondering if you all have
thoughts on that
because it's been unclear to me what
view they're using and how that relates
to the methods they're using
because when they talk about purpose it
seems very
sutrick it seems very like um
the world is bad we gotta we gotta fix
it we gotta fix ourselves we gotta chip
away all the bad stuff
and but then they use
tantric style emotional work like
biomotive encircling
for example
i am not you know i know
a little about monastic academy i know a
little about
um shinzon's approach
uh i'm not i don't think
i'm in a good position to comment
because
i i don't know enough about
how they're going about things um
circling
my understanding of circling is that
it's kind of pretty similar
to a lot of the um
the kind of gestalt work that i was
involved with
um you know the the the description of
what circling is like and
what the gestalt group work and then
there's there's also the
um who's called focusing or that kind of
background so i think
i'm reasonably familiar with those
kinds of group um
emotional work and dynamics um
yeah and i would say there is there
really is certainly a tantric flavor
to that methodology
um so where it ends up
uh you know if you're looking at
understanding emotional resonance
personally and in relation to others and
and
exploring emotional connection and
like how people are relating to each
other in
in the here and now in a circle so i'm
just going to cough
so if you if you're doing that kind of
exploration
then traditionally speaking that's not
cetric practice so that's not cetric
methodology that's not suitable practice
but if your
end point would then be
to say okay well
now that i understand that emotion i can
kind of leave it
behind whatever then that might be
heading towards a sutrac
um goal but i don't know enough about
what
they are doing to say whether they're
kind of bringing sutrick view
in at a later point or you know
whether it's just kind of mishmash of
views or or what i don't know
do you have any thoughts about that
jared have you you maybe have more
uh more knowledge of what's
of that of those systems that i do
i mean i i think uh my broad view
um of of a lot of the work is that
much of what we're seeing um that that
thing
with people like shinzen and everyone is
leading to
unique synthesis of
uh you know sutra tantra
uh maybe even a little bit of zogjan and
mahamudra
and then also uh incorporating a bunch
of
of therapy psychotherapy um you know so
because that seems to be the kind of
background uh
frame that all that us westerners come
to things from
um i don't you know because it's a
synthesis i think it can be really
tough to try and unpack uh just
you know what exactly it is um and
and then when you also factor in that
sometimes even if it's not explicitly
stated
in a system there can be
a tantric or citric influence
simply by the words that we use and the
common connotations that everybody has
with them
um so so it's yeah i i
i don't know i couldn't say that i have
the that i
have any kind of clear sense of the the
orientation um but it definitely seems
like
a lot of modern synthesis um
the reason i uh
the reason i went to got to uh vadriana
in some sense
uh was part of a
looking for a foundational way
or a a very uh non-abstracted view that
i could
employ to see what all of these systems
are and what they're doing and how
they're working
and uh and and that becomes more
available especially in very specific
contexts talking to somebody
how is this affecting you uh what what
what's what's working what's not working
um and this kind of goes to the
specificity of tantra
um and uh and yeah really this comes
down to
the fact that vajrayana uses these base
lenses
uh even though there's many of the other
ones with just emptiness and form
um and that for me is what kind of
wanting to to really embody those in a
deep way uh as kind of this meta view
even though
even though uh from a vadriana view it's
still saying that
it's not any more it's not more true in
some sense all of these are simply
different lenses that we can look at
things
um but but yeah that the emptiness and
form lens for me is like kind of the
most foundational that i've found and
it really does allow me to kind of move
between
different uh perspectives and to try to
see
what's working and how it's working um
and then yeah i
you could i could go in circles if we
were to like talk about something
specifically like oh yeah this is a
tantric
it's a method here uh but now it's
coming to a sutrich results or
uh or complying a citric view um
or or you know now aft after to
charlie's point after we've
uh stoked up these emotions in a tantric
way
now we're going to start relating to
them in the suture way so we can get rid
of them and yeah it's just
you know and then i could maybe you know
it just
it eats its tail in a lot of ways it's
really hard to to say that there's any
kind of
super consistent uh thing it's like it's
a messy world right
speak speaking to your point about
language jared
um and sarah
you're um relating back to what you were
saying as well
nearly everything
is presented in cetric language
and that's something i'm kind of very
keen to
[Music]
bring into awareness in the field so
you know pretty much everything if
you're if you're hearing the words
attention
focus um
concentration uh
um you know end goal uh
you know but particularly this sort of
whole language
around um who is who is the observer who
is the subject who's doing the watching
all of that is very very cetric language
um
you know you can get like there are
there are a slew of books written about
zogtra zog chair loads of books on zog
chen and
nearly all of them are written in
sutrich language
and so it doesn't you know it doesn't
matter if you have
a nice cover with zogchen and big fancy
letters on the front you've got like
some tibetan dude with 100 arms or
whatever like you know if the book
is about calming the mind and escaping
samsara and
you know achieving equanimity and
leaving
attachments behind you know this is
another very very
sutrich style of language
attachment and leaving attachment and
detachment and attack
detaching from emotions you know
all of that that is cetric language so
it's not
that that is a problem in itself it's
not to negate
the the the um
the validity of the practice but i think
it's
really really good to understand what
that is
to to be able to notice that and say
okay right
this is a description from the
perspective of sutra
or with cetric view because it's using
that kind of language
that can be just very helpful in
untangling what is being presented
in different synthesis and different
systems and what have you
and we don't really have a good language
for
tantra and zogjania you know those would
be very very
uh uniquely different i think in their
terminology and
you know i'm i often think about how
we're describing things and you know in
that whole
series that i did on um
um sheena and chalmetta and
the tmi series on my blog the difference
between
all of that i was really really careful
not to use the word
attention and not to talk about things
in terms of
attention and focus you know i may have
done at some point i don't remember
but i was very intentionally
using the language of shinee
to describe shinee practice rather than
using the language of tmi or
the language of sutra practice to
describe
shinee and that's you know those kind of
differences
are they're not easy to pick up on
either because the language of sutra is
so pervasive it's just so
everywhere it's just we're kind of
spiritually
immersed in that language now
um and i think other possibilities are
available
the more we kind of stretch it like the
dynamics of sutra which is just
basically kind of value judgments about
what is
good and bad in our experience um we can
also
move past the buddhist context and just
say like you know
you know judeo christian or christian uh
influences you know of heaven and hell
and sin and
and everything like that like you also
have some of those
similar dynamics yeah right yeah puritan
puritan influences tie in really well
with
with sutrix view yeah um
so i know we're right at our time so i
was thinking we could we could wrap the
recording up here uh
and then stop stop this and see if
anybody else wants to stick around
um but yeah i guess that being said uh
uh to the
to the viewers thank you for for tuning
in uh if you made it this far
uh sorry for our rambo let's plug our
patreon let's do oh yeah yeah
so evolvingground.org currently uh just
redirects directly to our patreon
um and uh and yeah we're uh we've gotten
a number of of uh early um
early yogi's signing up to support what
we're doing and we so appreciate it
thank you yeah it's you know it it's
just such a
vibrant fabulous community
we love you thank you and that being
said
you know we also so if you go there
there's a a little form
a link to a form at the top uh which is
available to anybody so if you
send in uh the form that kind of just
basically says you know a little bit
about your meditation background why
you're interested in vadriana
uh then you get invited to our our
little slack
channel we call the happy yogi slack and
um
and there's a ton of public content and
discussions and
uh you know all sorts of uh all sorts of
stuff going on
and cool conversations that's readily
available to anybody regardless of
whether you're a patron or not
uh but then yeah we have some perks for
people who uh are making you know kind
of a little
a little bit more um uh of a strong
commitment to working with us so
yeah i guess i guess that's all we have
for you today um and then uh you know
i don't know how many of these we're
going to do so the other video this is
number two
uh i mean to create the foundation we
probably have i don't know a dozen or so
or maybe a little less i have no idea
but hopefully uh
uh yeah we'll see what we have in for
for number three i don't even think
we've decided yet have we charlie
i don't think we've decided we've we've
taught with maybe principle and function
or uh what else have we
discussed you know maybe yeah confidence
we've talked about having one on
confidence
or transformation maybe or you know
we'll bring those things in but yeah
we'll uh
and if yeah if you want to if you if
you're not in the slack channel you want
to keep up with us i think the easiest
way is probably just on twitter
charlie and i are both uh fairly active
there
um my mind's at jared jane's and charlie
yours is at
underscore aubury awb ery
underscore perfect all right
thanks guys and uh we'll talk to you
next time